+55 (61) 99164-3843 Brasília, DF

cayanportela@hotmail.com

Cayan Portela

**Data Scientist** 

GitHub: cayan-portela LinkedIn: cayan-portela

With over 5 years of experience in data science, statistics and quantitative finance, working in medium and large companies. Experience in analyzing structured and unstructured data and solving business problems using data-driven techniques. Acting in process improvement, which results in task optimization, cost reduction and increased productivity.

### **SKILLS**

Tools and Languages

R, Python, SAS, SQL, GCP

Quantitative Research

Machine Learning, Statistical Modeling, Probability Theory

**Communication** English, C2 (EF SET 78/100)

### **EXPERIENCE**

Bank of Brazil

# Senior Data Scientist / globoplay (streaming platform)

2022 - current

Remote

- Growth Hacking: extracting insights focused on retention and acquisition metrics, leveraging business strategy.
- Next Best Offer: development of a supervised model to offer the best next product for each customer.

### **Data Scientist / Investment Division**

2019 - 2022

Brasília

- Development of churn models, identifying customers with probability of evasion.
- · Risk sensitivity analysis in investors portfolios.
- Automation of simulation models, providing pessimistic and optimistic scenarios forecasts.
- Implementation of external information via API and web-scrapping.

Volunteer professor

2019 — current

Brasília

- University of Brasília, UnB
- Contemporary Topics in Finance Data Science.
  Quantitative Methods and Models for Decision Making (2019/1).

### Statistician / Innovation, Regulation, Infrastructure and Credit Studies

2017 — current

Brasília

- Institute of Applied Economic Research, IPEA
  Econometric and quasi-experimental models for causal effect.
- Supervised and unsupervised machine learning methods.

Machine Learning Laboratory in Finance and Organizations

- Analysis of financial system indicators.
- Data visualization (interactive and static) and external data collection.

### Data scientist / Researcher

2017 - current

Brasília

- Unprecedented studies and research using machine learning applications.
- Consulting for interactive data visualization panel development.
- Delivering courses focused on data science and statistical computing.

### **EDUCATION**

## PhD candidate, Finance and Quantitative Methods, University of Brasília

Current

Msc, Experimental Statistics, University of São Paulo

2018

Bachelor, Statistics, University of Brasília

2015

### **PUBLICATIONS**

Feature selection and deep neural networks for stock price direction forecasting using technical analysis indicators Machine Learning with Applications, 100060, (2021)

Application of Machine Learning Ensemble Techniques in the Banking Industry

CFA Society Brazil, Honorable mention (2020)

The robot from Ipanema goes working: estimating the probability of jobs automation in Brazil

Latin American Business Review, 20.3, (2019)

Probability of automation of Brazilian occupations and Industry 4.0

https://lamfo.shinyapps.io/automacao

Published at Folha de São Paulo, Época Negócios and others.